Charles Wellborn papers, Inclusive: 1945-2009, undated, Bulk: 1951-1959
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Charles Wellborn papers
Inclusive: 1945-2009, undated, Bulk: 1951-1959
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3823
Wellborn, Charles Talmadge, 1923 - 2009
3 document boxes.
The Charles Wellborn papers contain sermons and other materials primarily from Charles Wellborn's time as pastor of Seventh and James Baptist Church in Waco, Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Charles Wellborn, born in Alto, Texas, to Charles F. and Ethel Swanzy Wellborn, grew up in East Texas and attended Gladewater High School. After graduating from high school, he attended Kilgore Junior College, where he won the national junior college debate championship twice. Wellborn received a full scholarship to come to Baylor University in 1942, but he joined the United States army shortly before graduation from Baylor. Through a series of clerical errors, Wellborn ended up in the 10th U.S. Army Division, the only unit of the army that was a ski unit, for the rest of World War II.
After the war ended, Wellborn came back to Baylor to finish his degree. Because of his prior school experience, he taught several courses in political science as he finished his degree. At that time, the Christian revival movement was sweeping Baylor, and Wellborn became part of it. He dedicated his life to Jesus Christ, and quickly became part of a team of college men leading revivals in major Texas colleges and cities. After finishing his political science degree, Wellborn began a master's degree in religion at Southwestern Theological Seminary and continued preaching at revivals across the South.
While still a seminary student, Wellborn recorded messages for "The Baptist Hour," and continued proclaiming the Gospel in revival meetings across the United States. After graduating and working for a time in Atlanta, Georgia, he was asked to become the pastor of Seventh and James Baptist Church back in Waco, which he accepted. Through his ten productive years as pastor of Seventh and James, Wellborn grew the church's membership exponentially and opened church membership to people of all races in 1958. Though he received threatening telephone calls and a cross was burned in his front yard in protest of opening church membership to everybody, Wellborn never wavered in his belief that the Gospel was for all people.
In 1961, Wellborn left Seventh and James and began studying for a doctorate at Duke University. He returned to Baylor University to teach religion for a time, but taught primarily at Florida State University for the rest of his career. He retired in 1990, and passed away in 2009. Florida State still honors him by hosting the Charles T. Wellborn Endowed Lecture Series every other year.
Scope and Content
The Charles Wellborn papers begin in 1945 and ends in 2009, with some undated materials. Of special note are the sermons written by Charles Wellborn during his time as pastor of Seventh and James Baptist Church in Waco and Faith Baptist Church in Kentucky. These sermons are the largest group of materials in the collection.
The Charles Wellborn Papers contain the professional writings of Pastor Charles Wellborn, a noted Baptist preacher and teacher during the mid-to-late 1900s. He came to know Christ, taught at Baylor University, and was pastor of Seventh and James Baptist Church, all in Waco, Texas, during this long and distinguished career.
Arrangement
This collection came organized by type with folder titles prior to this finding aid. Many of the folder titles were kept. No inventory was available prior to this finding aid.
Currently, the Charles Wellborn Papers are arranged in four series: I. Baptist Church Pastor, II. Religion Professor, III. The Baptist Hour, and IV. Personal Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3823. Acquired 2012-11-13
Related Resources
Related references
Allen, Bob. "Former 'Baptist Hour' preacher Charles Wellborn dies." Accessed 2012 December 13.
Bedell, George C. Religion in America. New York: Macmillan, 1975.
Shapiro, Michael W. "Friends Recall Pastor Charles Wellborn, who Integrated Two Churches in Waco, TX." Accessed 2012 December 13.
"Charles Wellborn." Waco Tribune-Herald. Accessed 2012 December 13.
Wellborn, Charles. "Oral Memoirs of Charles T. Wellborn." Interview by M. Rebecca Sharpless, 24 March 1999. Waco, Texas, Institute for Oral History, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects
Baptists -- Sermons.; Baptists -- Texas -- History.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; Revivals -- Texas -- History -- 20th century.
Genres
Articles.; Tracts (Ephemera)
- Baptist Church Pastor, 1945-2002, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains sermons written by Charles Wellborn during his time as pastor of Seventh and James Baptist Church in Waco, Texas, and Faith Baptist Church in Kentucky. While some complete sermons are written out, most are in outline form, with a list of the stories he wanted to tell to illustrate the point he was trying to make in the sermon. This series is in average condition.
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Correspondence, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (1 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (2 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (3 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (4 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (5 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (6 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (7 of 7), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (1 of 6), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (2 of 6), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (3 of 6), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (4 of 6), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (5 of 6), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: Revival (6 of 6), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 5), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 5), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 5), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (4 of 5), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (5 of 5), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 6), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 6), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 6), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (4 of 6), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (5 of 6), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (6 of 6), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 5), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 5), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 5), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (4 of 5), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (5 of 5), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: (4 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (5 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (6 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (7 of 7), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 3), 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 3), 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 3), 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 5), 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 5), 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 5), 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (4 of 5), 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (5 of 5), 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (2 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (4 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (5 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (6 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (7 of 7), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (1 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons: (2 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Seventh and James Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons (3 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Faith Baptist Church: Literary: Sermons, 2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Religion Professor, 2001-2009, undated; 2
  General condition: Excellent.
  This series contains a number of articles that Wellborn wrote for publication, probably when he was a professor at Florida State University. This series is in excellent condition.
  - Literary: Articles, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Literary: Articles, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Literary: Articles (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Literary: Articles (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- The Baptist Hour, 1951-1953; 3
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains tracts written by Charles Wellborn for the Baptist Hour, a regular radio program featuring sermons by prominent Baptist preachers. This series is in good condition.
  - Literary: Tracts, 1951 January (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Literary: Tracts, 1951 February-March (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Literary: Tracts, July-September (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Literary: Tracts, 1951 October-December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Literary: Tracts, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Literary: Tracts, 1953 January-February (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Literary: Tracts, 1953 March-May (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Personal Materials, 1953-2009, undated; 4
  This series contains several plays written by Charles Wellborn, eulogies and obituaries written about Wellborn, and other materials. The series is in excellent condition.
  - Literary: General, 1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Literary: Funeral Program, 2007, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Literary: Obituaries, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Literary: Eulogies, 2009 July-October 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Literary: Eulogies, 2009 October 3-2012, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Literary: Article: "A Question to Search Your Soul", undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Literary: Plays: "No More Darkness", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Literary: Plays: "Duel", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)